

COMPUTER ENGINEER · ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE EXPERT

207A Kloosterstraat, Lommel, Belgium

💌 axel.faes@gmail.com | 🌴 theaxec.github.io | 🖸 TheAxeC | 🛅 axelfaes | 🗲 Scholar | 🏛 KULeuven Who's Who

Abstract

I am a Msc. Artificial Intelligence and Msc. Computer Science Engineering student at KU Leuven. My main interests include program optimization, numerical linear algebra, artificial intelligence, virtual reality, neural computing and brain-computer interfaces. I am participating in the Honoursprogramme of the Faculty of Engineering Science (research track) at KU Leuven. I am also a big supporter of Open Source Software.

Research Interests

Programming Language Theory Algebraic Effect Handlers, Type Systems and Program Optimization **Artifical Intelligence** Machine Learning, Reinforcement Learning and Virtual Reality

Neuroscience Neural Computing and Brain Computer Interfaces

Educational background

Advanced Master of Science in Engineering (M.Sc.) in Artificial Intelligence

Leuven, Belgium Sep. 2017 - Jul. 2018

KU LEUVEN

Engineering and Computer Science

Master of Science in Engineering (M.Sc.) in Computer Science (Burgelijk Ingenieur - ir.)

Leuven, Belgium

KULFUVEN

UHASSELT

Artificial Intelligence & Theoretical Computer Science

Sep. 2016 - Jul. 2018

Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.) in Computer Science (79% - Magna Cum Laude)

Hasselt, Belgium Sep. 2013 - Jul. 2016

Physics and General courses

Business Summer School: United in Manchester (0739)

Manchester, UK

THE UNIVERSITY OF MANCHESTER

International Business

Jul. 2015 - Aug. 2015

Honors & Awards ____

Oct. 2017 Honoursprogramme, of the Faculty of Engineering Science KU Leuven, Belgium Sep. 2017 3rd place, ICFP 2017 Student Research Competition Oxford, UK Jul. 2016 Bachelor Award, in Computer Science UHasselt, Belgium May. 2016 3rd place, ACM CHI 2016 Student Design Competition (Interaction Design and User Experience.) San Jose, CA, USA Feb. 2016 **2nd place**, BeGDC (Belgian Game Development Championship) Brussel, Belgium Jan. 2016 IELTS, Academic Module (8.0/9.0) Brussel, Belgium

Work & Research Experience ____

Research Internship: Quasi-Monte Carlo points on collections of triangles

Leuven, Belgium Sep. 2017 - Current

- Faculty of Engineering Science: Computer Science
- Research group: NINES

Student Job: Creating System Identification course

KU LEUVEN

Leuven, Belgium

Faculty of Engineering Science: ESAT (Electrical Engineering)

• Research group: STADIUS

Sep. 2017 - Current

Research Assistant: design of type-&-effect system for Eff based on row polymorphism

Leuven, Belgium

KU Leuven Apr. 2017 - Oct. 2017

- Faculty of Engineering Science: Computer Science
- · Research group: DTAI
- Part of the Honoursprogramme of the Faculty of Engineering Science (research track).
- · Topic: Development of an row-based type-&-effect system for the Eff programming language

Research Assistent: efficient compilation of algebraic effect handlers

KU LEUVEN

Leuven, Belgium

Sep. 2016 - Apr. 2017

- Faculty of Engineering Science: Computer Science
- · Research group: DTAI
- Part of the Honoursprogramme of the Faculty of Engineering Science (research track). My project is part of the C1 project: Algebraic Effect
 Handlers: Harnessing the Fundamental Power of Effects. Eff is a functional programming language that uses handlers to handle all kinds
 of effects. These effects could be I/O, exceptions, user-defined, etc. My task is to design, implement, benchmark and formally proof new
 optimisations in the Eff compiler. The compiler is written in OCaml.

Web performance research intern

Hasselt, Belgium

EXPERTISE CENTRE FOR DIGITAL MEDIA (EDM), UHASSELT

Jul. 2016 - Sep. 2016

- · I worked on the iMinds PRO-FLOW project.
- My work involved creating multiple usecases to measure website performance. The main focus is on the difference between the http versions
 (http1.1, https, http2).
- During the project, I had to utilise multiple servers, maintain and extend the nodejs framework used to measure website performance, and manually optimize commercial websites using PHP, JS, HTML and CSS.

Summer Internship Physical Computing

Hasselt, Belgium

EXPERTISE CENTRE FOR DIGITAL MEDIA (EDM), UHASSELT

Aug. 2015 - Sep. 2015

Aug. 2015 - Aug. 2016

• Work on a project which focuses on the interaction between a human entity and a drone, aswell as interaction between the drone and virtual objects. This project is written in C++, used the Optitrack motion capture and a custom created drone.

Extracurricular Activities

KU Leuven Leuven, Belgium

Student Representative Sep. 2017 - Current

- POC of Master Computer Science Engineering
- POC of Advanced Master Artificial Intelligence
- Member of Departmental council of Computer Science
- · Member of Department board of Computer Science
- Member of Faculty council of Engineering Science

CoderDojo Belgium Uasselt, PXL

COACH Sep. 2014 - Current

• Teach children how to program utilising Scratch, Python, Minecraft and Lego mindstorm.

Student Council UHasselt

MEMBER

- Member of Board of Education
- Member of Faculty Council
- Member of Board of Student Facilities
- Member of Diversity Commission
- Temporary representative in WS (Vlaamse Vereniging van Studenten vzw)

Student Council UHasselt

Member Mar. 2015 - Aug. 2015

- · Member of Board of Education
- Member of Faculty Council
- Member of Board of Student Facilities

Natural Languages _

English Fluent (IELTS: 8.0/9.0)
Dutch Mothertongue
French Basic Knowledge

Projects

ICAL parser for KU Leuven schedules

Leuven, Belgium

LEAD DEVELOPER Aug. 2016 - Current

An nodejs application to create an iCalender file for courses at KU Leuven. Allows the creation of a schedule containing courses from different
masters and the option to ignore events.

Machine learning techniques for flow-based network intrusion detection systems

Hasselt, Belgium

BACHELOR'S THESIS

Feb. 2016 - Jul. 2016

• The thesis gives an overview of how machine learning algorithms could be used for intrusion detection using only IP Flows. The system has been used to detect intrusions in Cegeka Hasselt Datacenter network.

Software engineering: Search and Recommendation System

Hasselt, Belgium

TEAM MEMBER

Feb. 2016 - Jul. 2016

A search and recommendation system for VoD (Video on Demand) for Androme. The system is currently being used in production in the Nebula
project. Both Content-Based Recommendations and Collaborative filtering techniques were implemented. Made in a team of 5 (Pieter Teunen,
Luuk Raaijmakers, Brent Berghmans, Axel Faes, Matthijs Kaminski, Wouter Bollaert) utilising Java and the Spring framework.

TTUI: Household Survival Hasselt, Belgium

RESEARCHER

Sep. 2015 - Dec. 2015

- Project made for the class 'Technologies and Tools for User Interfaces'.
- A tower-defense style game written in Unity utilising Optitrack motion capture. The game combines the virtual world and reality, by allowing users to interact with the virtual world using real-world objects. Made by Brent Berghmans, Axel Faes and Matthijs Kaminski.

Cardinal: scripting language

Hasselt, Belgium

LEAD DEVELOPER

Jan. 2015 - Sep. 2015

- Cardinal is a small, fast, class-based, Object Oriented scripting language written in C. It is built upon the skeleton of an existing scripting language and shows how I can modify and improve existing software, as well as design new components to this software.
- · New components include a debugger, an embedding API, multiple inheritance and a new module system.

United in Manchester Manchester, UK

Team Leader

Jul. 2015 - Aug. 2015

A summer school which focuses on teamwork in cross-cultural and multidisciplinary teams, global product development and entrepreneurship.
 Our team developed a start-up idea on Food Management/Delivery system. Product pitch took place at the end of the course for feedbacks from professionals and for potential commercialisation. Our team consisted of Axel Faes, Linh Chi Evelyn Phan, Reinaert Van de Cruys and Maria Barouh.

PSOPV: Visual Programming IDE

Hasselt, Belgium

DEVELOPER

Feb. 2015 - Jul. 2015

 A Visual programming IDE created by Axel Faes & Matthijs Kaminski for a course of Hasselt University. The purpose of the IDE is to create 'black boxes' which can send events (signals packed with data) to eachother. We take the idea of using drag-able blocks in a visual IDE and expand on it.

Publications

CONFERENCE PAPERS

Robin Marx, Peter Quax, Axel Faes and Wim Lamotte, "Concatenation, embedding and sharding: Do HTTP/1 performance best

[1] practices make sense in HTTP/2?", WEBIST 2017 - Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on Web Information Systems and Technologies.

EXTENDED ABSTRACTS

Axel Faes and Tom Schrijvers, "Towards a core language with row-based effects for optimised compilation", International Conference on Functional Programming 2017 Student Research Competition.

Kashyap Todi, Brent Berghmans, Axel Faes and Matthijs Kaminski, "Purpose-Centric Appropriation of Everyday Objects as Game

[3] Controllers", CHI EA '16: Extended Abstracts of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. Late Breaking Work.

Kashyap Todi, Donald Degraen, Brent Berghmans, Axel Faes, Matthijs Kaminski and Kris Luyten, "Household Survival:

[4] Immersive Room-Sized Gaming Using Everyday Objects as Weapons", CHI EA '16: Extended Abstracts of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. Student Game Competition.

THESIS

[5] Axel Faes, "Machine learning techniques for flow-based network intrusion detection systems", Bachelor's thesis 2016.

POSTERS

[6] **Axel Faes and Tom Schrijvers**, "Towards a core language with row-based effects for optimised compilation", International Conference on Functional Programming 2017 Student Research Competition.

TALKS, PRESENTATIONS AND OTHER MEDIA

Sep. 19, 2017	"Honours student Axel Faes wins bronze medal in ACM SIGPLAN", KU Leuven, Department of Computer Science.
Sep. 19, 2017	"Student Axel Faes wins bronze medal in the ACM SIGPLAN Student Research Competition in ICFP conference", KU Leuven, Department of Computer Science, DTAI.